Alright, here we go. So, I'm going to follow
the homework master, aren't you happy? But
probably I'll get distracted and talk
too long and maybe won't even
finish the first class, but let's try.
Okay? So, here we go. I called the first
course ... and and the fun thing about this
teacher training is that I'm going to share
with you some of what was happening, why
I wrote the courses, you see what I mean?
Like what was happening, or what I was
thinking about, so if I can remember.
So, the first course is called the Principal
Teachings of Buddhism, but the real book
that I translated is called Lamtso Namsum (Lam-stzo rnam-gsum). Say Lam tso nam sum, which is short
for  "lam gyi tsowo
nam sum" okay? And ... okay I
was teaching Masha a new word yesterday,
where are you? She's disappeared. Oh
sorry, the pet peeve, hmm what's it mean?
Did she get it right Joel? My pet peeve.
No, I taught her an American idiom
yesterday. I'm American idiom teacher for
a lot of my students. "Pet peeve" means the
one thing that irritates me a lot. Okay?
And it's people who misspell Principal
Teachings of Buddhism. So, if you want to
fail your teacher training course just
spell it wrong.
Okay, so let's talk about it.
Principal (pal) means main, main teachings, okay?
And it's an adjective normally, except
for the Principal of a school which is a
man or woman who's the boss of the
school, okay? But principal teachings,
you're going to spell it with (pal) which
means "main teaching" okay?
What's principle mean with a (ple)? It
means an important idea okay? Like the
principle of gravity, or the principle of
relativity, okay? So get it straight okay?
Don't embarrass me in front of your
students.
I've seen many teachers do that okay?
We're talking principal teachings (pal)
okay? Some people have mistranslated it as ...
The Three Principles (ple),
but that's because they don't understand
that the tibetan word "tsowo" has to come
after what it modifies which is
extremely rare. Okay? So, "lam gyi tsowo" means, it doesn't mean
the "principles of the path" it doesn't
mean that. And many people are translated
that way, so you can just throw the book
out if you see that at the top, and you
don't know how many books I've thrown
out that way. It's ... so unfortunately
the word "tsowo" which means "main/primary", principal (pal) always comes after the
noun that it modifies okay? Like "book of
red" rather than "red book".
Okay, got it? Just nod. Sometimes the
adjective comes after then noun, this is a
"dress of red", you see what I mean? Meaning "red dress" okay? Anyway, people got confused
and it's a pet peeve, it irritates me
okay?
So you're not going to do that. Okay. So,
Three Main Paths of Buddhism
is the real title okay? I changed it to
the Principal Teachings of Buddhism to
make it easier, more? Accessible okay? More accessible. And the book, the translated
book with Tsongkapa on the front
is called The Principal Teachings of
Buddhism, it's not called The Three
Principal Paths okay? And it was meant to
be make it more accessible. By the way,
that painting, or that statue on the
front of that book, which is probably in the books there I
don't know? That's a real image of Tsongkapa, okay? It's the only one so it was
a real statue of Je Tsongkapa and it's got
a big nose and big ears and that's the way
he was okay? His enemies called him "Mr.
Big Nose" and he had a very big nose
okay? His face was very strong
okay? Fuerte, okay? And that's a real
picture. That statue was destroyed during
the Cultural Revolution, and they put
another one, they made another one that's
all pretty and handsome, and that's not
the real one okay? So, that's why it's
black and white because the photograph
was taken in the in the late 1940s or
something like that okay? Alright, so
you ... first course is based on the
Principal Teachings of Buddhism, which is
more correctly called? The Three Principal Paths of Buddhism.
The Three Principal Paths. Now, path (lam) in Tibetan. What is it in Sanskrit? Marga,
in this case doesn't mean "a road', and it
doesn't mean "a method", it doesn't mean
that. In the Prajna Paramita teachings
okay?
Topic number 4. "Path" is a synonym for
"understanding" or "realization" okay? It
means a mental state. Okay, so we're not
talking about three methods of Buddhism,
we're not even talking about three ways
that you can go in Buddhism, we're
talking about three attitudes
okay got it? And that's very important, if
you don't understand that you don't understand the course okay?
We're not talking about three methods,  we're not talking about three routes along a
highway, we're talking about three attitudes that are the principal
teachings of Buddhism, got it? So we're
not talking about books, we're talking
about ideas, three big ideas okay? And that's something you should know.
The author is? Je Tsongkapa. Okay sorry ...
"Je" means, by the way, "Lord". It's an honorable name like Lǎoshī, but
老師 is like elder teacher right, or something like that? it's like that. It's Je. Je means...
For example, diamond is called in Tibetan
"dorje" which means "king of stones." "Do"
means stone. Je means Lord, so Je
Tsongkapa means Lord Tsonkapa, it's a
respect word, okay? So, you can call him Tsongkapa, but it's
a little bit impolite, and if you call
him Je Tsongkapa it's more polite,
okay? Sometimes we call him "Je Rinpoche ", which means precious Lord. Rinpoche means like
you're like a jewel okay? So if they say
Je Rinpoche they're talking about Tsongkapa
okay? So you can use either one, it's kind
of weird to say Tsongkapa. Then a
lot of people spell his name with a (kh)
Tsongkhapa. Like many many people. That's a pet peeve of mine okay?
They are confusing the transliteration
with the sound okay? When you take a
foreign word and you put it in English,
you put the sound. You don't try to
capture the spelling in the in the
original language okay? Got it? Otherwise
you end up with things like "Sri Lanka" or
"Sivananda yoga center" which is both
mistaken, they're both mistaken. They are
failed transcription, they are not the
sound. Got it? It's a weird mistake. If you
see a book that has "Tsongkhapa" on
the front,  just throw it out. It means the person who wrote it
doesn't understand the difference between transcription and pronunciation,
got it? What's the transcription for Moscow? Moskva.
Moskva is the transcription, got it? We
pronounce it Moscow okay?
So got it? Don't put the spelling of the foreign language, put the sound
Okay got it? Tsongkapa, just "k", there's
no reason to put "kh", they messed up my
Lama's name at the passport agency.
He's Tharchin, okay? Because they saw the
the "th" in the transcription. Got it? It's so terrible to ruin someone's name
because you can't tell the difference
between the character and the sound.
Understand okay? You're never going to do
that, or I will get irritated ... more
irritated. Now, his monks name ... this is all,
I'm just working from the homeworks, is
say Lobsang Drakpa. Lobsang Drakpa. Lobsang means pure mind okay? "Lo" means mind and
"sang" means pure, and "b" as a prefix letter
Lobsang okay? Pure-minded one.
Sumati in sanskrit okay?
And his last name is Drakpa, which is
what in sanskrit?  Kirti, like Dharmakirti, Chandrakirti. Kirti means
"famous", everyone's heard of this guy, he's
amazing.
Okay? Super popular, okay? So, his name is
"pure-minded super popular" okay? That's
his monk's name. Now in the rules of monks names you take your ...  you take the first
name of the person who made you a monk
okay?
Like the normal abbot period in Sera Mey Monastery, for six hundred years, is four
years. So, during those four years
if the abbots name is Mike, then every
monk who's made that four years their
first name is Mike, and we had a big
problem at our Sera Mey because the
abbot stayed for three terms,
twelve years, half the monks in the
monastery are called Jampa, and it's really
confusing okay? You ... so my first name, monk name, is Lobsang and ultimately I come
from Tsongkapa you see? My teacher
teacher teacher teacher teacher got it?
Okay alright. Number 2, what's the
actual name of this work? Three Principal
paths, okay? You know that. It's not The Principal Teachings of Buddhism,
but it's the same "pal" okay? Alright.
Question 3. We're working through
homework number 1 yay! Now, in
Christian tradition there's a big
emphasis on epistles. What's a epistle?
It's like a heavy letter, like a letter
that became a classic. You know? The
letters of Paul right? The epistles of
Paul, which caused a lot of trouble ... he
wasn't even there. Okay anyway, epistle
means sacred letter, important letter.
Okay? So this book, the fourteen verses, is
a letter that was written toTsongkapa's
student named Nawang Drakpa,
okay? Nawang Drakpa. You're supposed to know that
okay? And you can read it in the reading.
Now, Nawang Krakpa had a crush on Tsongkapa
from the beginning, there's many paintings of Nawang Drakpa sitting at his
feet, so what did Tsongkapa do? "You go
to East Tibet and build a hundred and
eight monasteries", you know? And he's like, "what??!" So ... but he wasn't one of those lazy
disciples, he did what his teacher told
him to do, even though he didn't want to
go. That's the last thing he wanted to do
was leave his teachers side, but Tsongkapa
said "go, and don't come back until
you got 108 monasteries", okay? And he did it,
he went to east Tibet, he built a 108 monasteries.
Guess what's the name of the last one?
Datsang. Datsang. "Da" means "now", "sang"
means "I reached the full number".
Complete, haha total! The last monastery was
called "total", got it? I made the total. Datsang. And it's a
famous monastery, I used to know the
abbot okay? it's a cool ... it's a good
monastery. It's still running okay? So this
book was written as a letter to his
student ,who was upset because he got
told to go out to east Tibet okay? And
he's trying to like ,what do you call
it? Soften him up a little bit yeah. "Don't
get irritated with me" you know? "Here, I'll
give you a nice summary of all of
Buddhism in two pages",  he's like, "yeah okay, that's cool." By the way,
for $50. Okay, I'm not saying you're
interested in money and not Dharma, I'm
just saying it makes it more fun for me
okay? Frankly, it's more fun for me.
Ready? In the ACI 18 Foundation Courses
there's another important letter sent to
Nawang Drakpa. Why? What's the letter say? Yeah. Nawang Drakpa made the first monks in
East Tibet, and he wrote a letter to his
teacher and said, "look, I not only
built monasteries, I ordained a bunch of
monks." And? This is the answer by Tsongkapa.
Don't say, "yeah". You want money or you
don't want money honey? Okay, he forgot. I
saved the money, cancel that one
Shaoping okay?
You just lost 25 bucks. Okay ... he told his
student,
does anyone remember? Come on! Yeah.
"You want to meditate, it's not the seat,
it's not the legs, it's not the face, it's not the breathing, it's not the
topic, it's? Yeah! Did you respect other
people's peace of mind last week? Or did
you irritate other people? And the letter
is is incredible you know? And by the way,
in DCI we teach them, you know, level
3, we teach meditation for like
hours after hours, then at the end we say
it doesn't matter. Nothing matters. What
you hear in your mind is coming from how
you treated people last week. Don't worry
if your left foot goes up first, your right
foot goes up first, you know? Can you
slouch, can you not slouch, do you exhale
long enough or not. Forget all that stuff
okay? If you want to have a good
meditation, don't upset other people's
mind okay? Be conscious to not upset other people's
mind. Speak kindly to people, speak with
careful consideration to how they feel.
Watch their face, if they go like that [grimmace], then back off because you're planting
seeds to hear crap in your mind while
you meditate, okay? You're planting seeds
for your mind to go, "yeah what's for lunch, what's for lunch?"
Okay? That comes from irritating other people, like teaching them Ashtanga,
stuff like that ... ok, just kidding. Ok, he has a nickname okay? Say Tsako
Wonpo. Tsako Wonpo. By the way, here
the the [homework] master is mistaken, okay?
The old [homework] master from 27 years ago it's misspelled, his name is misspelled.
Okay it's Wonpo, and Tsako is an area
that he came from, like like Kansas or
Suzhou, or something okay? Like, it's
some ... Dalian, some faraway place okay? Wonbo
means, it means like a friendly word
for local priest you know? Like the
little local priest. Tsako Wonbo okay? Little local priest from
Tsako. Ok, so sometimes you might see
him name spelled Tsako Wonbo.
Ok alright? I didn't put his dates, guess what?
He lived in the same time as Tsongkapa. Alright. Umm, I also try to
leave out stuff that is going to overload
you okay? I mean, I could put more and
more stuff and we you would never finish
the course okay?
it'd be like the Lamrim okay! The
commentary you are studying was written by?
Pabongka  Rinpoche, and the whole
translation is the course. Ok? The whole
translation is in the course, whole commentary is in the
course. Ok, got it? I translated .. I remember where
I translated it. I was on a one-month
retreat in near the Grand Canyon and I
remember. I remember I translated it
there. Ok? Dates of Pabongka Rinpoche.
1878 to 1941. Now, he was probably the
most famous teacher of the Tsongkapa
tradition for that hundred years okay? He
was number one, ok? So I'll tell you a
little bit about his story and you can
read it in the book okay? So, in the book ...
I got my teacher, Khen Rinpoche Geshe Lobsang Tharchin,
I got him to tell me the story about Pabongka Rinpoche okay? And it was hard because he
didn't like to answer my questions, but I
offered to drive him to Washington every
month, which is a five-hour drive and he
couldn't get out of the car, so he told
me the whole story okay? So it's in the ... by the way, his nephew which
is Geshe Lobsang Thardu was brought up by Khen Rinpoche as a from childhood and
became his main attendant, and he became the khansen gergen. What's that
mean? He became the house mom, the
babysitter, for all the monks in our
college. There are 12 colleges in Sera Mey, according to the ancient constitution
of Sera May, which we found in Russia. The
only copy, we found it in St. Petersburg.
And there are 12 houses, 12 colleges,
inside of Sera, Sera Mey Monastery. Sera
is divided into two halves, Sera Jey where
they're not so educated, and Sera Mey
which is vastly superior. And there's a
heavy rivalry between the two halves, and
there's a green line in the monastery.
There's an invisible line and you don't
cross it or something might happen okay?
Tough stuff happens in the monastery,
you have no idea okay? But you don't go
over that line. So, we're from Sera May
okay? And we don't like Sera Jey okay? And
there's lots of nice teachers at Sera Jey,
but don't tell anybody. okay. So, anyway
Sera Mey has 12 colleges. You're from
Gyalrong College okay? You are affiliated as my student ... you are affiliated with Gyalrong
College. So, in the structure of Sera ... of
all the great Tsongkapa monasteries,
there are, what do you call? "Local houses", meaning ... when I went to
Princeton we had an Arizona Club, and all
the students from Arizona we used to
drink beer together, stuff like that okay?
And so in the monastery there are local
houses and Gyalrong is East East East
Tibet ...
.... their language is totally
weird okay and not quite Tibetan. okay? So anyway, for some reason
my teacher was put into Gyalrong house by his uncle or something
at the age of 7 or 5 okay? And the
highest Lama in history from our college
is Pabonghka, he's Gyalrong house, got it?
He's from your college so you got to be
loyal okay? He's from our College, okay got it? Which is a great honor
okay, to be from his house, and I
had the honor of debating with the third
one okay? The third Pabongkha, he was
doing his Geshe the year before I did
my Geshe, and he's from our college.
Tradition in the house is you have to
defend yourself, Geshe examination in your house before
you defend yourself in the monastery,
before you defend yourself in
Sera, so he had to defend himself in our
college and we only had 50 monks there,
but the person who attacks him first is
the senior student who's not a Geshe yet,
which was me. So, I was supposed to attack him first.
So I'm attacking Pabongkha in the debates
and that was my job. Guess what question
I asked him?
After you get enlightened and you become
a Buddha, how can you help suffering
beings because you don't have the karma
to see people suffering anymore? You see
them as high-level bodhisattvas, all
beings become high-level bodhisattvas in
your heaven, so how can those people help
suffering beings after they become a
Buddha? It's they all became humans
instead of dogs you see? [using the pen example to understand emptiness] So, there's no
chew toys, got it? In the universe for them.
So we started like that, and I was really
getting him, but when the opponent is a
high Rinpoche and you're just a schmuck,
the debate master will call off the
debate. He'll say "O la so", which means
"okay next!", and I was like "I got him, I got
him" he says "o la so", and I'm like "dang!" And then
we went on the porch and continued the
debate for 3-4 hours, and it was cool.
And the abbot of the Tantric College was
with us and we ....
okay .... O la so! Anyway, that's Pabongkha Rinpoche, he has a nickname in the
secret teachings, in the Diamond Way
teachings, we don't call him Pabongkha
Rinpoche, we call him Dechen Nyingbo, say
Dechen Nyingbo. Dechen means the bliss
that's associated with seeing emptiness
in Tantra okay?
Great bliss, and Nyingbo means Xīn,
heart .. heart .. just heart okay? Heart of
Bliss okay? So, that's his secret name but
sometimes you'll hear him called Dechen Nyingbo okay? He was the greatest teacher of
his time. He graduated from my monastery,
our monastery, Sera Mey from Gyalrong house,
but he was not a high Geshe, he was not
a number one Geshe, he was like a number
three level Geshe, which is what I am. If
you want to be a number two level you
have to wait another four years, if you
want to be another one level it might
take 10 more years and I'm too old, and I
probably couldn't do it anyway. So, it's
much more examinations okay? But it's interesting that he was also a
third-level Geshe, he was not a high
level Geshe, but he did something
strange which is that he started
teaching normal people, and it was very
very unusual, and then ten normal
people ... not monks came to his class, then
twenty came to the class, than thirty
came to his class, by the time he taught the
Lamrim you're studying in the morning,
there were a thousand people in the room
okay? And he became famous for teaching
normal people, he was the DCI of his time,
and the ACI of his time, you see? And he
got heavily criticized, very very heavily
criticized, and it was a very serious
thing. You could be murdered in
those days, and he he stuck it out you
know? You're going to see two photos of him.
One is a young handsome guy okay, then
five years later
he looks terrible, he looks like somebody
beat him up you know? And they say he was
attacked by spirits, he had a war with
spirits, he had like a one-year war with
a bunch of spirits and it cost him
physically. He never recovered physically
okay? You can see the two photos, it's
very interesting. So that's the story. So,
he used to come to monasteries and teach
the Lamrim, which is what you're
studying in the morning, maybe for a
month okay? And that's, by the way, how a
Geshe gets the Lamrim teachings. You get them because a lama visits and teaches them extra-curricular, it's not part of the program,
it's dessert okay? So, they will cancel all the
classes for a month and some high high
Lama will come, like Pabonghka Rinpoche and he will teach the Lamrim
for a month, and then they'll invite all
the local people to come and that's
what's happening in the morning, that's
what you're hearing in the morning okay?
So, then there's a nyerpa, say nyerpa. Nyerpa means the refreshment person okay,
and you're ... okay, a monastery kitchen, like at Sera Mey,
we have to go serve in the kitchen, every
two weeks we have to spend two days
there, something like that, when you wash
the teapot you need a ladder to get up
to the top, and then you need another
ladder to get in and then you clean it
like this ... it's tea for 3,000 people
okay? And so that's the nyerpa, the
nyerpa runs the tea at the Lamrim
teaching which has a thousand people,
everyone's got to get tea, everyone's got
to get tsampa porridge okay? So, my
teacher ... and by the way usually only pick
the lazy monks, you don't pick the Geshe
candidates because they're too busy
okay? So, they have a miksel. Miksel means
they don't have to do the dirty work in
the monastery, they can just study all
day. They're pampered, the good Geshe
candidates are ... you don't bother them,
they don't have to work like other
people okay?
My Lama was a goofball okay? Goofball
means bad boy, never studied, just played
tricks on people. His favorite trick ... you
know thumbtack? Like small nails, so
people in Tibet inside the monastery
they don't wear shoes, understand? He
would spread thumbtacks all over just
for fun then he'd watch them you know? And
he was really naughty, he was really bad.
Papza, say papza, "pap" means little piece
of flour, like you make flour and then
you make little balls like that ... and then
when you're in the prayer, 3000 guys, they're all going .... sangye chudang tsokyi choknam la ...
You know, when they go waaah, and you go [shooting dough ball sound], you know like 10 feet away, three meters, [shooting sound] and ....
he was the best, my teacher was number one, and he didn't study, he didn't do
anything, so that's why he got stuck with
nyerpa, he had to make refreshments and
he was doing it and Pabongkha visited
the kitchen, to check on the refreshments for the teaching, and he saw
my teacher and he walks over to him and
he puts his hands on his head and he
says, "this one is special, this one is
special", then he just turned around and
left you know? Yeah! And then something weird happened to my
teacher and he freaked out, he got
some kind of ... I don't know what, spirit
from Pabongkha and he changed totally, and he was offered a very important
position, very good money, big temple you
know? Rest of your life you drink tea and
eat offerings, and he said no. He told his
teacher, "no I'm not going" he said 'you're a
fool, you know the rest of your life
you're going to be wealthy, it's a good gig."
You know? And he said, "no I want to be a
Geshe."
He said, "you a Geshe?!" And my teacher said "I'm going to be a number one Geshe!" Ok?
He's like, "number one Geshe, yeah, yeah right!"
"When you become a number one Geshe, I
become the throne holder of Tsongkapa!"
You know? And my teacher got pissed off and he worked really hard, and he became a
number one Geshe, and then in his year they had a competition of all the number one
Geshes, and he beat all of them so we
call angi dampo, he was number one of, I
don't know 20 thousand monks okay? In
the debates. So, try to win an argument
with him, you know? If he says the sky is
not blue, he can prove it, you know don't
even try to fight with him, just go
around him understand? Ok, I still do
that. Um okay, now "pabong" means "boulder", and it's a
special hermitage, retreat center outside
of Sera, you can walk to it, you have to
hike to it. It's like Diamond Mountain,
it's very similar to Diamond Mountain, so that
retreat center was called Pabong,
so he was called Pabongkha, but he was
not Pabongkha okay? They decided he would be the incarnation
of the abbot of Pabong ka, but he wasn't so what's the story?
He's actually recognized as the
reincarnation of ... say, Changkya Rolpay Dorje.
Very very famous lama of the emperor of
china, and there's still a temple in
Beijing, and I've seen it, dedicated to Changkya okay? So, this is a
very famous teacher of the king of China,
the Emperor of China, okay?
And still the that temple is still there, I've seen it, you can see it from the
hotel if you get to the 20th floor because it's surrounded by other
buildings you know, and it's really cool,
alright? Then, he was very friendly with
China and he really got along with with the Chinese, so in the year that Pabongkha
was born there was a lot of tension and people were afraid to call
him his real name, Changkya, so they called him Pabongkha, okay understand? They
named him a different name because there
was so much tension, political tension
okay? Anyway, that's who he really is. 1717
to 1786.
okay Changkya, this Changkya. Very very
famous, and he wrote four volumes ...
Siddhanta, mister Word for zero dollars!
Yeah, a study of all the schools, we kind
of did a Siddhanta yesterday okay? But he
was a ... he wrote the biggest and the most
famous okay? In his past life.
Alright now, but Pabongkha Rinpoche had a
special student okay, who wrote down his
teachings and these are the days before
iPhone recorders okay, and people were
taking notes like crazy and the Lama's
just teaching, no microphone. A thousand
people, you had to have a big voice, you know?
And so his student was a high Lama
called Trijang Rinpoche, say Trijang
Rinpoche. Born 1901 passed away in 1981
okay?
And Trijang Rinpoche became the highest
Geshe of his time and taught the Dalai Lama
okay? He was the Dalai Lama's teacher and he was an amazing kind person,
amazing scholar, amazing teacher, and why
we have the Gift of Liberation, why
we have that book, is he he spent 12
years editing those talks, and I believe
it's the greatest book ever written in
Tibetan okay? it's the ... it's the sweetest
Tibetan language that ever was written. It's perfect, the book is totally perfect.
The Tibetan is exquisite, and they're ... you
know nowadays because of the Cultural
Revolution etc., the level of Tibetan in
Tibet is low, it's ... I called a monastery
many years ago to find a book, no one
could speak Tibetan okay? So, I believe
that's going to be the greatest book ever
written in Tibetan, and it was edited by
Trijang Rinpoche. Trijang Rinpoche was my teachers root Lama okay, so you're Trijang
Rinpoche's grand ... great grandkids
okay, got it? It's a good lineage, good
lineage. Ok.
So the person who wrote the introduction
to your course, and it's on your homework,
is Khen Rinpoche, Geshe Lobsang Tharchin, my teacher okay?
Born 1921 passed away 2004 okay, alright and he taught me for free for 30
years, and I lived with him for 25 years okay? And it was hard,
he was a hard person, you could never win
an argument, he never once told me I did
something right. When I finished my Geshe, first
foreigner in 600 years, he's he's like "huh" ... so his nephew was his closest
disciple, and I'm pleased to say he's going to visit this week okay?
He's very old now, he's about 80 and we
put him on a plane, he agreed to come, and
I asked him to give a teaching about Khen
Rinpoche, which is your grandfather okay?
And just to tell us about his personal life,
you know, like tell us some nice stories. Geshe Lotar is his name, he's not a high
Geshe, he's not a great scholar, but he's
a great storyteller, he's like the best I
know. and he did become the debate master of Sera Mey,
which is kind of like assistant abbot, it's vice abbot okay? So he did reach
this position, and he ... he helped me
survive in the monastery okay? Without
him I wouldn't have survived, I was the
only foreigner to survive in Sara Mey
still, in 600 years, and it's only because he was so ... he'd say,
"the green line's there, don't cross it, don't cross it, don't walk over there", I'm like "I
don't see anything", He's like, "trust me"
you know? And my whole career in the
monastery is due to him, he taught me to
tie my robes, you know everything. Dressed
me up for the Geshe exams, it's like getting married. No, it's like three
layers of stupid historical stuff, and so you should be grateful to him, you should
make him some nice offerings okay? Red
envelopes, and you should respect him
okay? Without him I wouldn't be here, okay?
And he taught me to speak Tibetan
because he never stops talking, which is probably good luck for me okay?
And we lived together for about ten
years, so uh he's good. So, you're going to get a
nice ... and I I don't think he'll be able to come again, so I think it's kind of a
special chance okay? What day is that Tim?
Yeah, he'll be staying here but but he'll
give a lecture on Saturday morning okay?
So, anyone's welcome to come okay?
Now, the text doesn't jump right into the
three principal paths it starts with
some preliminary material which is
traditional okay one of them perhaps the
most traditional thing to say first is
as you listen to this teaching avoid the
three problems of the pot okay, which we
covered in? Kamalashila, so there ... as
long ago as the Tang dynasty, Tang Cháo,
1,700's?
700's. Xuanzang? 1,300 years ago, as early
as that, they were talking about this
idea called "the three problems of the
pot" okay? For zero dollars! Ok, 1
dollar, give me any of them, give me one each,
raise your hand and give me one. Don't yell.
Ok, Jasso. Yeah okay, somebody else!
You do that in the Geshe debates and you're in trouble, huh? Yeah, don't .. don't  .. you
can't pour water into a dirty cup, okay? So, what's it mean? Let's do the other two,
yeah, give me another one. Huh? Yeah, don't be like a cup with hole in the bottom,
okay? The teacher teaches, and teaches,
and teaches, and it leaks out, and I ask
you a question the next day and you're like 'huh?" What was yours? Did you have another
one? Yeah, upside down. Like, the teacher
tries to pour in the stuff, but you're
already full with with other ideas, you
know you went to some shaman ayahuasca
ceremony and you know, you're not open to
these ideas ... these three ideas okay?
You're already ... you're off on some strange thing okay? I had a student from
Ireland, she she actually translated the mandala offering into Gaelic, what do you call it?
Celtic, and it was amazing and then she was a very good student here, and
then she she went to a ayahuasca ceremony and she said I'm going to record it, she
turned on her video, they overdosed her. She died on the video, you can watch it
okay? Okay, stupid idea, got it? Don't fill yourself up with dumb "spiritual",  you
know, okay got it? You can talk to her father
who's the head of the Ireland group okay? Sad, very sad okay? So, anyway don't be
like a pot ... the three things you should go into the teaching ... before the
teaching starts okay, be open, okay I'm going to learn something new, I'll
be open ... it's not what I'm used to, but I'm open to it. It's like the yoga class
we had this morning, the teacher
said ...  first thing he said, "look I'm going to
do stuff you didn't do before, just be open okay?' That's the first pot,
be open to it. Yeah, second one is: don't mix it up
with other stuff, and as an ACI a teacher if you mix it up with other stuff I'll
kick you out in five minutes okay? Ready? You mention ayahuasca in a ACI course
and I will kick you out, clear? Do I have to say it again? Ok? You're
teaching ACI alright? Now, does that mean
you can't teach something else next week?
No, I'm not like that okay? I understand everyone in the room comes from a
different tradition, you know maybe you're from a Jewish tradition, maybe
you're from a Christian tradition, maybe you're from a Muslim tradition, and maybe
you're going to be teaching in a Muslim
country, then say cool stuff about
Muslim okay? That's fine, but don't do it
in the middle of the course,
don't mix it with this course okay? This
course is ACI, this course in Tsongkapa,
it's a formula for enlightenment, if you add ayahuasca it won't work anymore,
people will fail, people will suffer for more billions of years got it? Okay, so I
request, I don't request, I order! Don't mix
other stuff with ACI, it doesn't mean you
can't teach other stuff, you want to
teach something else, do it next week. Don't do it in the middle of the ACI
class okay, understand? I request, no I order, and I
will remove your certification if I find out you're mixing it with other stuff
okay? It's a formula, it works, I can tell
you it works, it happened to me ... stuff
happened to me that is extraordinary,
unbelievable, so no one in the world can
talk me out of it, people have tried, and I just laugh, you
know like, "what are you talking about?" "You follow this correctly, you can see
the whole universe in your meditation, you can meet every living creature,
billions, you know, don't tell me ayahuasca."
Ok, I'm not interested. Then they're like, "Yeah but Geshela", and I'm like "yeah but
get out!" I'm not interested, you know? I
already have a Model X, don't try to sell
me a Volkswagen bug, okay? And I'm not,
what do you call ... sectarian. I tried it, it
worked, I got what I wanted okay, and I say you can do it too,
but not if you mix it up. You're going to ruin the recipe okay, understand? Okay. And
it's not because other traditions are bad, it's not the point, you know? You
don't put a mapo tofu recipe with a chocolate cake recipe right? One is
spicy one ... it's not going to work out, it's
going to be the worst thing anyone ever
made okay? Mapo tofu is nice, chocolate cake is
nice, don't mix them. Let's do one one day and serve it to everybody,
wouldn't that be fun? Luca, no? Let's serve it tomorrow in class so people remember
what I said, you're all going to throw up. Mapo
tofu chocolate cake. Okay ... maybe I'll make it just just so you remember, you'll tell
your students, "yeah, your grandfather Lama Geshe Michael, back in the old days, he
made us eat a chocolate mapo tofu cake okay, and it was terrible, so please don't mix
up the teaching." Okay, who's going to make it, Candy you want to make it? Come on!
You guys are ... I better teach lama ... obeying your lama
here um ... okay ... all Lamrim texts have three great divisions, all Lamrim texts have
three great divisions, the teachings A to
Z, one two three, step four, one two three
four five, how to get to Buddhahood, have three big divisions okay? And they depend
on the motivation of the person in the class okay, so we kyebu chung, say kyebu chung.
kyebu dring. kyebu chenpo, okay? They're
called little people, middle people, and
big people okay? But literally the word
is little people, medium people, and big
people okay? Now, it's just a difference
of motivation. Who's going to tell me little
people's motivation? it doesn't refer to your height, it refers to your
heart. Huh?
Is that what it says? Yeah, I don't want to go to the lower birth okay? I don't want to
go to the lower birth alright? I don't want to be reborn as
an animal, in the hell, or as a spirit okay? I don't want to go through the
lower births. That's little people's motivation. For a
hundred, three hundred? I'm spending
too fast, right Shao Ping? I'd make it a
thousand ... hmm ... okay thousand bucks, but I pay you later ... seriously ... what's the one
teaching that would satisfy a small person, what they want? You owe me a thousand.
You owe me thousand. I'm ahead already. Sheesh! Good cancelled! Ahh.
The pen, okay? The pen, alright? A person
who understands the pen teaching
correctly, cannot go to a lower birth. It's not possible okay?
You destroy all the seeds in your being that would send you to a lower
birth, and can you imagine people complain that I teach it too much!
They're going to thank me later okay?
If you understand the pen correctly,
jor lam supa is the technical term: the
mastery level of the path of preparation,
which is when you have a deep
understanding of the pen, and the holder
of the pen by the way. You cannot go to
the lower realms, it's not physically
possible, okay cool? So forget "little person" you
already passed that okay? What's medium person? Yeah, I don't want
any kind of samsara.  I don't want any kind of suffering life
okay? I don't care if I become President,
or I become a garbage man. It all sucks, I
don't want any of it okay? I want to be ... I
want nirvana okay, for? Me. Okay, then
that's a hint about the big person. Big
person wants? Yeah, yeah they want
everyone to be enlightened okay?
Bodhisattva. Bodhisattva. So, these are
the three great divisions of the Lamrim
teachings okay? Alright, here we go ...
Question nine, I'm making it, I got three
minutes Tim, I'm going to do it. Ahh ...
question nine, name the three principal
paths. Okay, they are called renunciation,
which is a big English word that nobody
uses. It doesn't pass the waiter test.
What's the waiter test Shao Ping? Loud!
Good. When we decide in our translation
team whether to use a word or not
I send Allison to the Mexican restaurant and I say, say to the waiter
what does renunciation mean? Say to the
waiter, I'm Chinese, look, I don't know
English very well, what's renunciation mean? If the waiter
can't answer you, don't use it in your translation, but I did because that was
27 years ago okay? And that's what I was
taught alright? And it's not a great
translation okay? It's not a great translation. Renunciation ... okay now follow
me okay? Now we're going to do content.
Renunciation means: I will not ride in a fancy car, I will not have a lot of money,
I will eat only dal and rice you know? And bananas.
I will live simply, I will not dress nice
clothes you know this is the classical
meaning of renunciation okay, and it's not what we want, it's not what we want
you to do okay? It's not ... we talked about it yesterday okay? If you practice
Buddhism properly you will be successful whether you want to be or not, and you
can run but the money will follow you I'm sorry okay? And fame, and clothes, and
cars, and ... they will chase you down the street
you can't avoid them okay, if you plant ...
if you understand seeds, and you plant
seeds only to serve other people, you
will still be super successful I'm sorry.
Okay, how many of the great Saints of Buddhism were princes? Shantideva,
Asanga, Siddhartha, okay? Atisha, okay? come on! Okay, got it?
So it doesn't mean you have to run away
from money and cars and girlfriends
okay? It doesn't mean that! Okay? It
doesn't mean that. It means: recognize
that if you don't figure out the seed system everything around you is going to
collapse and die including you okay? If
you don't figure out how to plant more
seeds than you use up, you will die, and
you will not have money, and you will not
have a partner, and you will not have
happiness, okay?
It doesn't mean you shouldn't have a partner, or money, or happiness,
it doesn't mean that. okay, got it? That's
not renunciation okay? I tried to go to a
cave, I did go to a cave, I spent I don't
know a month in a cave, it's not a good
place, there's bugs, I had a I had a
highly deadly rattlesnake, a green
rattlesnake, bite you once you're dead,
there's no cure.
I had a wolf come in, I had spiders
crawling over me all day, it's not cool
okay? That's not renunciation. Get a place
with a door okay? Get it ... if you can find
a cave with a door okay, but I thought
somehow a cave would be more holy or
something. It's not, it's just irritating.
Okay got it? Have a nice ... I like to say I
like a small house, but I want it elegant okay? Why? I hate cleaning.
I don't want cleaning, I don't want a
house with five rooms in it. If you are ...
somebody offered me one recently, you
know his name, and I said no I don't want
it. He keeps asking me, he said I built it
for you, I said I don't want it you know?
I don't want a house that I have to
clean all day you know? I want a small
house, elegant, you know sweet, cool, elegant, tasteful like but small ... less cleaning
okay? So, that's renunciation, got it? You can have a nice house
it's fine, okay got it? It's not renunciation to wear bad
clothes, and to not have a job, and to wander
around and stay on other people's couches and ... I don't let those
yogi's in my house why? They always leave
the refrigerator empty, these "holy" people
okay? They always park on your couch, you go to
work to pay for the couch, and then your
refrigerator is empty when you come home.
I don't want you to be like that okay?
That's not an ACI teacher, that's not a
yogi, that's a bum, that's a dharma bum
okay? Make your own money, be responsible
that's a Dharma teacher. The best ... you
know I made a list of the best ACI
teachers I know, and they're all
responsible people, some of them have
families, some of them have high jobs you
know, own own big companies, but they're
responsible got it? I would say that's
one of the most important qualities of
a ... I'm not going to trust you with my life
if you can't feed yourself, you see what I mean?
I'm not going to trust you with my
spiritual life if you can't figure out
how to make fifty dollars a day. Understand? Got it? Okay alright ...
Second one, okay so first principle path, call it
renunciation because I don't want to
change all the masters, but what it means
is: I'm tired of seeing the suffering of
the world, I'm tired ... I'm tired of it okay?
I'm tired of it, that's all, that's all. I can't take it anymore
okay? These wars in Syria in ... you know
Israel, Orit's friends got a missile
dropped on them a few days ago you know? I'm tired of seeing this stuff you know,
I'm tired of these crazy things going on,
I'm tired of people dying all around me
you know, it makes me ... I'm tired. Okay, that's the first
principle path okay? What are you going to
write on homework? I'm tired.
That's all I could take, I don't want it anymore okay?
I don't want his people dying around me
okay? it's so lonely, my old lady ... her
worst suffering is that she's the last
one, there's no one she can call, they all
died. Okay, and it will happen to us, it will
happen to you okay, there will be a day
when the the last person from this
training dies okay, so I'm tired, I don't want to see this anymore,
I want to fix it okay, that's the first principle path, got it? I'm tired. If you
want to show off your English put
renunciation, but I'm happy to take "I'm
tired" on the homework, I'm tired of this
stuff, you know let's fix it, let's get it ...
let's stop this. There are planets where
they stopped it okay, there's whole
planets where people studied ACI and no
one dies anymore, and no one has to meet
irritating people anymore okay? Everyone
has a model X, until model Z comes out,
okay? Everyone's happy because they understand
Buddhism, and every planet goes through
this evolution. Some are already finished,
some are halfway through like us, and
some didn't get Buddhism yet okay? I'm
tired of it okay, that's the first one, first principal path, second principal
path? It's called bodhichitta okay, if
you see a book that says "Buddha mind"
as a translation of bodhichitta, throw it
out, okay? They don't know what they're
talking about you know, people always
give me books at the airport. "Oh here
Geshela, here's a book," you know, I'm
like "oh thanks," I go through customs and I
throw it out on the other side, especially if it says "Bodhi mind" or
"enlightenment mind", come on, okay. It means, ready? The wish to become
enlightened, it doesn't mean an enlightened mind
that's already enlightened, duh!  Got it okay? You have it before you
become a Buddha, mainly. Okay, I want to
become enlightened so I can split my
body into a billion pieces and help all
the people who are suffering of things
that I'm tired of. Got it? It's natural next step okay?
I'm fed up with seeing people die. Then
what are you going to do about it?
Hey, I'm going to become Buddha because then I can split my body and teach ACI in a
billion planets, instead of just one country on the internet got it? Okay?
That's ... that's all. I call it the Wish for
enlightenment, and I capitalized the W
okay? I'm fed up with bodhichitta, "chitta"
does mean "mind," "bodhi" does mean
"Buddhahood",  bodhichitta doesn't mean
"enlightened mind",  it's a bad, super
bad translation. That's a James Brown song ... super bad ... it's
super bad okay, got it? it doesn't mean that at all, if you see that in a
translation just ... it means the rest of the book is bad also okay, if they didn't
figure that much out, okay got it? Pet peeve, bad translations
are 90% of my irritation, Word is the
other 10% ... just kidding. Okay, third
principal path, if you want to become a
Buddha to help all living beings,
you got to see emptiness directly, that's
all. Third principal path, call it "wisdom",
but you know in English wisdom means
like wise person, they don't drive too
fast, they don't eat stuff with a lot of cholesterol in it, that's not wisdom,
we're not talking about that, we're talking about
have you seen emptiness directly okay? You CAN be a person like that, if you
follow this class if you follow these teachings, if you do the meditations, you
learn here, you can become an Arya, you
can join Nagarjuna, Asanga, Tsongkapa,
you have everything you need. Everyone in
this room has access to the direct
perception emptiness, and most of the people outside this room don't okay?
Honestly, frankly, okay, you have
everything you need to see emptiness
directly. If you see it, in the same hour,
you see every planet and every person on
every planet, and you love them intensely
during that hour, got it? Then what else
is going to bother you your whole life? How can anyone make you upset or
irritated, you know they're like "I don't
like what you cooked for dinner." "Hey man, I
saw all the billion planets okay, calm
down, I don't care what you think about
my dinner" got it? You can't irritate an Arya ... almost, unless
you have bad translations and stuff, but uh okay, I mean ... what's there to talk about if you
saw your own Buddhahood, okay in the
future you saw the day and you know it's
coming, and then who's going to irritate you?
I mean certain ... if Andrea's teaches
a really heavy yoga class maybe ... but come on, isn't that worth it? Just to do
the ACI ... see emptiness so nobody can
irritate you, that's worth it right?
That's worth coming here a bunch of
times okay? So, you can do it okay, and
that experience that happens right after
you see emptiness directly, in the same
hour, there's nothing like it okay? What
happens the hour before you see
emptiness directly? Come on! Give me some specifics ...
you see a seed opening in your own mind, for the first time in ... in Mind-Only
language, you catch the storehouse
opening, you ... you see, and it always
happens like that, okay technically jor
lam chu chok, just before you ... an hour
before you see emptiness directly, for the first time you see that this laptop
is coming out of your seeds, coming from
you okay, everything. Then who's going to
piss you off after that? You know, your
husband who yells at you ...
he's also coming from you, if you want to punch somebody, punch yourself okay, got it,
understand? So, all these things happen, you confirm
dependent origination one hour before
you see emptiness directly, because
dependent origination just means: stuff
is coming out of seeds in your mind okay,
and you see it directly, why can't you see it before that? Geshela's been
teaching you, year after year, why didn't you see it? It's too fast, it's
65 a second, you got to meditate
okay, you got to have good meditation okay
got it? Good seeds. Alright, those are the three principal paths, let's review.
Number one? I'm tired, god bless! I'm tired, okay?
Number two? I want to be a Buddha to help
the universe, I'm headed for the stars
next week, I'm finishing this planet this week, I got it wrapped up by Sunday and
then I'm headed out okay? That's intention okay, you can say the
Wish, capital W, I'll take it on the homework
okay, what's ... by the way I finished the
homework Tim, it took me ... the master, it's
like six pages good luck. I didn't write
the homework for tonight, but I'll do it by morning okay?
Third one? Yeah, they call it DPE, I didn't invent that, it's not so bad,
somebody changed their car license to
DPE ...
direct perception of emptiness okay, alright, okay got it?
Those are what ACI course 1 is all about, that's the only ... main subject of
ACI course 1 okay? So, all of Buddhism is
covered in ACI course 1, why did you
do the rest of the courses Geshela? I
don't know, it was just fun okay mmm ...
the last homework question, I'm not
giving you a break okay, you got to pee
pee, just get up and go okay, you're allowed.
Yes, but it's gotta be really good because otherwise I won't finish the
class, okay it's not good alright ...
the last question is: are these three
principal paths physical, mental, or are
they concepts? Mental, they are attitudes,
they're attitudes okay, they're not paths,
they're not concrete. They're not even instructions, they're
not Sutras, they're ideas, they're ways of
thinking, attitudes okay? Should have been
called the Three Principal Attitudes ok. Alright, I finished homework one, let me
finish ... you sure? Okay there's no microphone I'm sorry .... oh okay, three
problems on the pot: number one, you're
not open to learning, you're
upside down. Number two, what you hear, you mix it up with other, you know
ayahuasca shaman stuff. Number three, you are leaky. Geshe-la
teaches you something tonight you forgot
it by tomorrow, got it?
You don't hold it, you don't retain it.
Okay alright, we're going to the second
homework you guys okay?